The past, the present and the future will all meet at the crossroads of hell!
Hellraiser: Bloodline is a horror, science fiction,
thriller film directed by Alan Smithee.
Three generations of the same family deal with the
consequences of unleashing the forces of hell.
Phillip L'Merchant / John Merchant / Dr. Paul Merchant, played by Bruce Ramsay.
Angelique, played by Valentina Vargas.
Pinhead, played by Doug Bradley.
Genevieve L'Merchant, played by Charlotte Chatton.
Jacques, played by Adam Scott.
Bobbi Merchant, played by Kim Myers.
Hellraiser: Bloodline (also known as Hellraiser IV: Bloodline) is a 1996 American science fiction horror film
and the fourth installment in the Hellraiser series, which serves as both a prequel and a sequel.
Directed by Kevin Yagher and Joe Chappelle, the film stars Doug Bradley as Pinhead,
reprising his role and now the only remaining original character and cast member.
It also features Bruce Ramsay, Valentina Vargas, Kim Myers
and Adam Scott in his first major film role.
It was the last Hellraiser film to be released theatrically and the last to have any major
official involvement with series creator Clive Barker until the 2022 reboot.
In the 18th century, Phillip LeMarchand a celebrated toymaker (Ramsay) is hired to create his greatest work, the Lament Configuration,
not knowing that it will allow the summoning of the demonic Cenobites, including Pinhead (Bradley) and Angelique (Vargas).
Hundreds of years in the future, the toymaker's descendant Dr.
Paul Merchant (also played by Ramsay), an engineer, has designed a space
station that he believes can trap and destroy the Cenobites.
Major themes include time, toys and game-playing, adultery and slavery.
The film had a troubled history and, after completing the film, original director Yagher
left the production when distributor Miramax demanded new scenes be shot.
It was subsequently completed by Chappelle.
The new scenes and re-shoots changed several characters' relationships, gave the
film a happy ending, introduced Pinhead earlier, and cut 25 minutes.
Yagher felt the changes diverged too strongly from his vision and was granted the Alan
Smithee pseudonym, an alias used by directors who want to go uncredited.
Miramax released it in the United States on March
8, where it grossed $9 million.
It was not screened for critics and received negative reviews.
The film explores themes of artificial intelligence
(a.i.), hell, engineer, pinhead, demon.
The tone is dark and thought_provoking and intense.